Guide to the Ezra Laderman Papers
Yale University Music Library
Ezra Laderman Papers
1924-2015
MSS 133
Yale University Music Library
96
71
100 containers
Laderman, Ezra, 1924-2015
Scope and Contents
The Papers are focused principally on Laderman's prolific career as a composer. Virtually all of his compositions are held in the collection, including chamber music, orchestral works, operas and musicals, oratorios and cantatas, and scores for film and television. The collection contains many sketches and drafts, which give insight into Laderman's compositional process. The collection also contains a significant number of reel-to-reel recordings of Laderman's works.
The remainder of the collection consists of correspondence, writings, clippings, programs, documents and awards. The correspondence is divided into three subseries: Correspondence with significant figures; Correspondence by subject; and Correspondence by date. Researchers are advised to consult all three subseries when looking for material on a specific topic. The Writings, Professional Activities and Photographs series contains a range of material related to Laderman's roles as President of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, Chairman of Music Programs the National Endowment for the Arts, and Dean of the Yale School of Music. Researchers should also consult the Correspondence by Subject subseries for correspondence related to Laderman's professional activities.
Clippings, publicity, and programs span the whole of Laderman's career – from the 1940s through 2015. The Documents and awards series includes items such as degree certificates, school report cards, and award plaques.
Biographical / Historical
Ezra Laderman ranks among the leading American composers of his time. Born in Brooklyn in 1924, he was educated at the High School of Music and Art, Brooklyn College, and Columbia University; his teachers included Stefan Wolpe, Miriam Gideon, Otto Luening, and Douglas Moore. Service in the U.S. Army during World War II interrupted his formal education, but not his compositional career; after participating in the liberation of Leipzig, he wrote a symphony inspired by the experience.
Laderman was a prolific composer in a range of genres; he produced numerous symphonies, concertos, and chamber works, and he created operas based on characters as varied as Galileo Galilei and Marilyn Monroe. His music has been performed by many leading ensembles and soloists, including the New York Philharmonic, the Chicago Symphony, the Philadelphia Orchestra, Yo-Yo Ma, Emanuel Ax, Elmar Oliveira, and Jean-Pierre Rampal. His musical career spanned several eras; he began composing as a boy in the 1930s, and he continued nearly until his death in 2015.
Laderman was an educator and administrator as well as a composer. He taught at several institutions, most notably the Yale School of Music, where he served as Dean and as Professor of Composition. He was Chairman of Music Programs at the National Endowment for the Arts, and President of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Music Center, and the National Music Council.
Separated Materials
Duplicates of manuscript scores, and published, ummarked scores have been separated from the collection.
Arrangement
The Papers are divided into seven series: I. Music; II. Audiovisual material; III. Correspondence; IV. Writings and professional activities; V. Clippings and publicity; VI. Programs; and VII. Documents and awards. The Papers were received in several installments over a period of thirty years. The collection was partially processed in the 1990s, which influenced its current arrangement.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- Archives; Laderman, Ezra, 1924-2015
- Music
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes a wide variety of formats: pencil sketches, pencil manuscript scores, Ozalid transparencies and copies, annotated photocopies, and computer printouts.
  Many of the scores include yellow sticky notes with identifying information. These were written by Ezra Laderman himself. Unidentified pieces and fragments are filed at the end of this series.
  Arrangement
  Pieces are listed in alphabetical order by title. All versions of each piece (e.g., sketch, manuscript score, printed score with edits) are kept together. In some cases, the number of versions necessitated housing the material in multiple boxes.
  Note that listed dates can refer to the date of composition and/or date of publication.
  - Chamber, solo and choral works, 1945-2013
    Includes works for small ensembles, solo instruments, voice, and keyboard.
    - Adagio For Strings, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      For string quintet.
    - Aldo, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Written for the Yale Cellos, an ensemble conducted by Aldo Parisot.
    - Brass Quintet, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brass Trio, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cadence for Two Flutes and Strings, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Can It Be?, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      For voice and piano.
    - Candida, no date (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Canons, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      For two instruments.
    - Celestial Bodies, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      For flute and string quartet. For Samuel Baron.
    - Cello Partita II, no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cello Sonata, 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Charter (The), no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
      For clarinet, trumpet, horn and cello.
    - Dance Quartet, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      For dancer, flute, clarinet and cello.
    - Decade, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
      For piano. For Robert.
    - Divertimento, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
      For flute, oboe and bassoon.
    - Double Helix, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      For flute, oboe and strings.
    - Double String Quartet "Octet", 1986 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Duet for Flute and Dancer, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Duetti for Flute and B-flat Clarinet, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Duo Concertante, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      For two pianos.
    - Duo (Blizzard of '96), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      For 2 cellos.
    - Duo for 2 Bassoons, no date (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Duo for Cello & Piano, 1984 (Box 13)
    - Duo for Violin and Cello, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Duo for Violin and Piano, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Duo in Two Parts for Flute and Cello, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Written for Isaiah and Rachel Laderman.
    - Early Piano Pieces, no date (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Multiple pieces: Despair, Freedom, Panic, and Theme and Variations.
    - Echoes and Anticipation, 1976 (Box 14)
      Chamber concerto for oboe and seven instruments. 3 movements. For solo oboe, flute, clarinet, violin, viola, cello, piano, and percussion.
    - Elegy for Solo Bassoon, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Elegy, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      For viola.
    - Endings, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Instrumentation not specified. Probably for violin and piano.
    - Enjoy, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Five measure klezmer phrase for clarinet.
    - (To) Entertain a Ghost, no date (Box 2, Folder 5)
      For voice and woodwind quintet. Includes script for play by Louis Peterson.
    - Ephemera, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      For piano.
    - Epigrams and Canons for Two Baroque Flutes, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Epilogue, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      For clarinet, violin, cello and piano.
    - Equity, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      For unspecified solo instrument (treble clef) and piano.
    - Etudes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      For solo piano
    - Etudes, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      For solo piano.
    - Fanfare for the Ravens, no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
      For two trumpets and percussion.
    - Fanfare Serenade for Gerald, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      For flute, clarinet, trumpet, horn, tuba, violin, and 2 celli.
    - Fanfare for the Uncommon Couple, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      For trumpet and percussion.
    - Fanfare for Yale, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      For brass and percussion.
    - Fantasy for Cello Solo, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Fantasy for Four Flutes, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Fantasy on 2nd Piano Concerto, no date (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Five Trios and Fantasy for Woodwind Quintet, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Flute and String Quartet, no date (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - For Ann and Gerry [Weismann], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - For Bass Clarinet, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - For Flute and Cello, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - For Fontana, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - For John, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      For solo cello.
    - For Judy for Flute and Piano, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - For Laura and Matt [Segal], 1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - For Life - Be Love, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      For string trio.
    - For Pearl, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Instrumentation not specified.
    - Four Pieces for Piano, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Fractured Night, no date (Box 3, Folder 6)
      For violin and piano.
    - Grand Duo: Across the Seas, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      For two pianos. For Tanya and Steve.
    - Grand Partita for Viola, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Handful of Souls, no date (Box 3, Folder 8)
      For chorus.
    - Helen Anderson 70th Birthday Piece, no date (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hershel, no date (Box 18, Folder 11)
      For clarinet, violin, viola, cello, and bass. Includes script.
    - Image of Love, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      For voice. One page of vocal part.
    - Interior Landscapes, no date (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Introduction, Barcarolle, and Allegro for Flute and Harp, no date (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - July 30th for Solo Flute, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - June 29th for Solo Flute, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - The Learning Tree, no date (Box 3, Folder 14)
      For flute, bassoon, horn, 2 celli, harpsichord, and percussion.
    - Les Adieux for Violin and Piano, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Lied for Piano Quintet, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Lilli, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Little Lost Sheep, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Long Time Between, no date (Box 3, Folder 18)
      For SATB choir.
    - Machinal, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Instrumentation nor specified. Probably for piano.
    - Ma Tovoo, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - MBL Suite, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      For string quartet and two flutes.
    - Meanings of Art - Book II, no date (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Instrumentation not specified. Probably for chamber ensemble.
    - Meditations, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Instrumentation not specified. Probably for solo cello.
    - A Moment in Time for Solo Flute, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Momente for Piano, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Motet, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      For soprano and SATB choir. For Mary Green.
    - Music for Winds, Strings, and Harpsichord, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Net Spot, no date (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Nonette, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      For quartet (instruments not specified).
    - Octet for Winds, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - On Vinyard Sound, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      For guitar.
    - Ondine for Solo Flute, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Organ Music for a Special Event, no date (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Other Voices, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      For three violas.
    - Parisot, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      For multiple celli (four staves).
    - Partita, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      For solo violin.
    - Partita (Contrasts for Cello), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Partita for Cello I, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Partita for Solo Cello, Meditations on Isaiah, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Partita for Violin, no date (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Piano Pieces, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      3 pieces.
    - Piano Sonata, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Piano Sonata No. 1, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Piano Sonata No. 2, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      "Scherzo from this piece is a sketch for the third movement from Piano Concerto No. 2." [Noted by Ezra Laderman]
    - Piano Sonata No. 3, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Piano Sonata No. 3, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      1st and 2nd drafts.
    - Piano Sonata No. 3: Circus of My Mind, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Piano Sonatas: Draft Sketches, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Piano Trio, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Trio for violin, cello, and piano.
    - Piano Trio No. 1, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Piece for Clarinet, Cello, and Harpsichord, no date, probably 1957-58 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Pieces for Viola, no date, probably 1957-58 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Pieces for Violin, Cello, and Harpsichord, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Pinsky Songs (Box 5, Folder 1, 4-6, Box 6, Folder 1)
      I. First Early Mornings Together; II. Sonnet; III. Love Crown; IV. The Want Bone; V. Antique; VI. As I Drew Nearer; VII. Food; VIII. Chaim Bialik's Light; At Pleasure Bay; Light; Ode to Meaning; Canto V; Samurai Song, and [Untitled]. Also includes libretti, and an unpublished printed copy of "The Pinsky/Laderman Songs."
    - Portraits for Violin, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Prelude, no date (Box 6, Folder 3)
      For string quartet.
    - Quartet No. 1 for Trumpet, Horn, Trombone, and Piano, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Quartet No. II Epilogue, no date (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Instrumentation not specified. Sketch of piano score included.
    - Quartet No. 4, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Quartet No. 5, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Quartet No. 6, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Quartet XII, no date (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Quartet for Flute and Strings, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Quartet for Oboe, Violin, Viola, and Cello, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Quartet for Piano, Violin, Viola, and Cello, 1996-7 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - The Question Tree, no date (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Quintet for Clarinet and String Quartet, 1987-88 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Quintet for Harpsichord, Flute, Oboe, Viola, and Cello, no date (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Quintet for Piano and String Quartet, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Quintet for Piano and Strings, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Scenes From an Imagined Childhood, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      For vocal ensemble and piano.
    - Scenes From an Imagined Life - Book I, 1997-98 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      For clarinet, violin, cello, and piano.
    - Scenes From an Imagined Life - Book II, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Scherzo, no date (Box 8, Folder 1)
      For viola and piano.
    - Serenade for Clarinet, 1957-58 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Sextet, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      For strings.
    - Sextet, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      For woodwinds and strings.
    - Sextet for English Horn, Bass Clarinet, and Strings, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Sextet for Winds and Bass, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      For woodwind quintet and string bass.
    - Sh'ma, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      For SATB and accompaniment.
    - Simões, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      For six celli.
    - A Single Line, Elegy for Solo Violoncello, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      For Stephen Kates.
    - A Single Voice, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      For cello.
    - A Single Voice, for Flute and String Quartet, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - A Single Voice, for Oboe and Strings, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Solo and Chorale, no date (Box 9, Folder 1)
      For flute, clarinet, and cello.
    - Sonata No. 3 for Piano, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Sonata No. 4 for Piano, no date (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Sonata No. 5 for Piano, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Sonata No. 10 in C Major, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      For flute, clarinet, oboe, and bassoon.
    - Sonata for Clarinet and Piano, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Sonata for Flute and Piano, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Sonata for Violin and Piano, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Sonata for Violincello and Piano, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Song of Songs, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Chamber version.
    - Songs for Eve, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      For soprano and piano.
    - Songs for "The Odyssey", 1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      For male voice and guitar. Text by Gilbert Highet.
    - Songs From Michelangelo, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      For baritone and piano.
    - The Spring, no date (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - String Trio No. 1, no date (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - String Quartet No. 0, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - String Quartet No. 1, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - String Quartet No. 1, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - String Quartet No. 2, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - String Quartet No. 3, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - String Quartet No. 7, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - String Quartet No. 8, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - String Quartet No. 9, 1996-99 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - String Quartet No. 10, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - String Quartet No. 10A, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - String Quartet No. 10B, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - String Quartet No. 10C, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - String Quartet No. 11 (Fantasy Quartet), 1999 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - String Quartet No. 12, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - String Quartet Sketch, no date (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Suite for Michael #3, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Instrumentation not specified - for solo instrument in treble clef.
    - Suite for Two Pianos, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Talkin' - Lovin' - Leavin', 1991 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      For string quartet and alto recorder.
    - Theme and Variations for Violin and Piano, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Theme, Variations, and Finale for Four Winds and Four Strings, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      For flute, clarinet, bassoon, horn, violin, viola, cello, and bass.
    - Time Stood Still, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      For solo voice and piano.
    - Three Pieces for Clarinet, Cello and Piano, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Toccata, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Trio, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      For clarinet, violin, and piano.
    - Trio (I), 2012 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      For flute, clarinet and bassoon.
    - Twenty-Five Preludes for Organ, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Two Preludes "Metz" for Piano, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Dedicated to Camilla Frank.
    - Variations, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      Instrument not specified. Probably written for piano.
    - Violin Duets, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Violin and Marimba Duos, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Where Does It End?, 2008 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Woodwind Sketches, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      For woodwind quintet.
    - Woodwind Quintet, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Worship, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Written with Norman Rosten. For voice and piano.
    - You Are Not Alone, no date (Box 18, Folder 8)
      For flute, oboe, clarinet, and bassoon.
  - Orchestral Works, 1945-2004
    - Concertos
      - Chamber Concerto, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 3)
        "Dance work for Jean Erdman featuring Donald MacCale at the Brooklyn Academy."
      - Concerto for Bass Clarinet and Orchestra, 2001 (Box 15)
        For Richard Page and the Pittsburgh Symphony.
      - Concerto for Bassoon and Strings, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
        Written for Bernard Garfield, National Orchestra Association, with Leon Barzin.
      - Concerto for Chamber Orchestra, 1989 (Box 13)
      - Concerto for Clarinet and Strings, 1993-94 (Box 16, Folder 1)
        For David Shifrin
      - Concerto for Double Orchestra, 1988 (Box 14)
        "For the New Jersey Symphony Orchestra and Hugh Wolff."
      - Concerto for Flute and Orchestra, 1985 (Box 15)
        "Affectionately dedicated to Jean-Pierre Rampal, Gunther Herbig, and the Detroit Symphony. Commissioned by the Detroit Symphont Orchestra for Jean-Pierre Rampal."
      - Concerto for Flute, Bassoon, and Orchestra, 1989 (Box 15)
      - Concerto for Orchestra ("Satire"), 1966-1974 (Box 19)
      - Concerto for Piano and Orchestra, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Concerto for Piano and Orchestra, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Concerto for Piano and Orchestra, 1977 (Box 17)
      - Concerto No.2 for Piano and Orchestra (Second Piano Concerto), 1989 (Box 17)
      - Concerto for String Quartet and Orchestra, 1979 (Box 17)
        For the Alard String Quartet. Premiered by the Alard String Quartet, Andre Previn, and the Pittsburgh Symphony.
      - Concerto for Timpani and Orchestra, no date (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Concerto for Viola and Orchestra, 1977 (Box 19)
      - Concerto for Viola and Orchestra, 2002 (Box 19)
        For Toby Appel. Includes orchestral score and piano reduction.
      - Concerto for Violin and Orchestra No. 1 "Chai Irvi", 1951 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Concerto for Violin and Orchestra, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 5)
        1961 date crossed out on score and replaced with "1951".
      - Concerto for Violin and Orchestra, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Concerto for Violincello and Orchestra, 1984 (Box 15)
      - Concerto for Violincello and Orchestra, 1986 (Box 15)
        "Dedicated to and commissioned by the Syracuse Symphony Orchestra, Kazuyoshi Akiyama, music director. In commemoration of the 10th anniversary of the Tchaikovsky Competition gold medals of Elmar Oliveira and Nathaniel Rosen."
      - Variations on a Passacaglia (Concerto for Cello and Orchestra), 1994 (Box 13)
    - Symphonies
      - Sinfonia, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Sinfonia Concertante, 1988 (Box 25)
      - Symphony No. 1 "The Leipzig", 1945 (Box 21–22)
      - Symphony No. 2 Luther, 1968 (Box 23)
      - Symphony No. 3 "Jerusalem", 1973 (Box 23)
      - Symphony No. 4 "Symphony for Brass and Orchestra", 1980 (Box 23)
      - Symphony No. 5 Isaiah, 1982 (Box 23)
      - Symphony No. 6, 1983 (Box 24)
      - Symphony No. 7, 1987 (Box 24)
        Dedicated to Eduardo Mata and the Dallas Symphony.
      - Symphony No. 8, 1992 (Box 13)
      - Symphony "Yisrael", 1997-98 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Symphony in Three Movements for Winds and Brass, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Additional Orchestral Works
      - Citadel, 1985 (Box 40)
        Also known as "Citadel Symphony for Orchestra".
      - Epilogue, 1954 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - Fantasy On Clinton Hill, 1957 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      - Identity, 1957 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      - In Gansett Woods, no date (Box 42, Folder 4)
      - International Atom, no date (Box 42, Folder 5)
      - Nonetto di Notte (Nonette of the Night), 2004 (Box 40)
      - Pentimento, 1985/86 (Box 42, Folder 6)
        Also known as "Aggionamento".
      - Phoenix Organization No. 1, 1951 (Box 40)
      - Priorities, 1975 (Box 40)
      - Sanctuary, 1986 (Box 40)
      - Sonore, 1983 (Box 40)
      - Stanzas 1-6 for Chamber Orchestra, 1959 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      - Summer Solstice, 1980 (Box 40)
      - Tercentennial Fanfare, 2000 (Box 40)
        Fanfare for orchestral brass and percussion.
      - Thema and Variations, no date (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Operas and Musicals, 1950-1969
    - Air Raid, 1967 (Box 26)
    - Dominique, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Galileo, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 2, Box 28, Box 25, Box 27A)
    - Goodbye to the Clown, 1960 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Hunting of the Snark, 1964 (Box 26, Box 29, Folder 2-3, Box 29A)
    - Jacob and the Indians, 1954 (Box 29, Folder 4, Box 30, Folder 1, Box 29A)
    - Marilyn, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 5, Box 27, Folder 1, 1A, Box 27A)
    - Rappaccini's Daughter, 1950 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Sarah, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Shadows Among Us, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 3, Box 31, Folder 1, Box 26)
  - Oratorios and Cantatas, 1960-2013
    - And David Wept, 1971 (Box 31, Folder 4, Box 33, Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Brotherly Love, 1999 (Box 31, Folder 3, Box 32, Box 33)
    - Canto V, 2012 (Box 24)
    - Columbus, no date (Box 24, Box 34, Folder 2)
      Also titled "Visions Columbus"
    - Esther, 1960 (Box 24)
      A dance drama.
    - The Eagle Stirred, 1961 (Box 24)
    - Magic Prison, 1966/70 (Box 35)
    - Questions of Abraham, 1973 (Box 36, Box 34, Folder 3, 3A)
    - Song of Songs, 1968 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Thrive Upon The Rock, 1969 (Box 37, Folder 2)